[
    [
        {
            "id":1,
            "question":"The average monthly salary of 60 employees of a factory is Rs.29900. If two officers are getting Rs.90,000 each and the average salary of 8 supervisors is Rs.65,000, then what is the average salary (in Rs.) of the remaining employees?",
            "options":[21080,22680,29080,21880],
            "answer":21880,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":2,
            "question":"In an examination, the average score of a student was 67.6. If he would have got 27 more marks in Mathematics, 10 more marks in Computer Science, 18 more marks in History and retained the same marks in other subjects, then his average score would have been 72.6. How many papers were there in the examination?",
            "options":[11,10,12,9],
            "answer":11,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":3,
            "question":" The average weight of students of section A and B having 40 students each is 45.5 kg and 44.2 kg respectively. Two students of section A having average weight 48.75 kg were shifted B and 2 students of section B were shifted to section A, making the average weight of both the sections equal. What is the average weight (in kg) of the students who were shifted from section B to section A?",
            "options":[34.5,35,35.75, 34.25],
            "answer":35.75,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":4,
            "question":"What is the average of numbers from 1 to 50 which are multiples of 2 or 5? (correct to one decimal place)",
            "options":[25.4,25.9, 26.4,25.8],
            "answer":25.8,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":5,
            "question":"What is the ratio of the average of first eight prime numbers to the average of first ten even natural numbers?",
            "options":["1 : 7","7 : 80","8 : 70","7 : 8"],
            "answer":"7 : 8",
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":6,
            "question":"The numbers 2, 3, 4 and 5 occur (2+5k), (5k-7), (2k-3) and (k+2) times, respectively. The average of the number is 2.85. Later on, the number 2 was replaced by 6 in all the places. What is the average of the new numbers?",
            "options":[2.4,5.25,3.85,4.75],
            "answer": 5.25,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":7,
            "question":"x, y and z are three positive numbers such that y is 4/5 times of x and z is 5/8 times of y. If the average of reciprocals of the numbers x, y and z is , then 17/240 the average of 3 times of x and 5 times of y will be:",
            "options":[70,60,40,45],
            "answer":70,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":8,
            "question":"The average of the numbers a, b, c and d is 2d-4, Also, the averages of the numbers a and b: b and c: c and d are 8, 5 and 4, respectively. If e = a+d+1, then what is the average of the numbers d and e?",
            "options":[8,10,3,7],
            "answer":10,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":9,
            "question":"If the average of the 3-digit numbers 335, 2x5, x35, 63x and 406 is 411, then what will be the average of (x-1), (x-3), (x+3) and (x+5) ?",
            "options":[6,3,5,4],
            "answer":4,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":10,
            "question":"The average weight of a group of 3 people A, B and C is 70 kg. When D joins this group, the average becomes 60 kg. One man E whose weight is 5 kg more than that of D, replaces A and the average weight of B, C, D and E now becomes 59kg Aâ€™s weight (in kg ) is:",
            "options":[50,40,39,59],
            "answer":39,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":11,
            "question":"The average of 35 consecutive natural numbers is N. Dropping the first 10 numbers and including the next 10 numbers, the average is changed to M. If the value of M - N = 600, then the average of 3M and 5N is:",
            "options":[90,120,100,115],
            "answer":115,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":12,
            "question":"The numbers 24, 45, a, 35, 59, 83, 46, b, 29, 74 are serially numbered as they appear in the sequence. When each number is added to its serial number, then the average of the new numbers formed is 55. The average of the missing numbers (a and b) is:",
            "options":[38,58,62,50],
            "answer":50,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":13,
            "question":"The average of nine 2 digit numbers is decreased by 6 when the digits of one of the 2 digit numbers is interchanged. Find the difference between the digits of that number.",
            "options":[6,4,2,8],
            "answer":6,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":14,
            "question":"The average of four consecutive odd natural numbers is eight less than the average of three consecutive even natural numbers. If the sum of these even numbers is equal to the sum of above four odd numbers, then the average of four original odd numbers is:",
            "options":[36,24,18,32],
            "answer":24,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":15,
            "question":"A batsman in his 11th innings makes a score of 77 runs, thereby increasing his average scores by 3. What is his average score after the 11th innings?",
            "options":[46,49,47,48],
            "answer":47,
            "category":"Average"
        }
    ],
    [
        {
            "id":1,
            "question":"Out of 6 numbers, the sum of the first 5 numbers is 7 times the 6th number. If their average is 136, then the 6th number is:",
            "options":[84,96,116,102],
            "answer":102,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":2,
            "question":"The average age of husband, wife and child 7 years ago was 42 years and that of wife and child 9 years ago was 36 years. The present age of the husband is:",
            "options":[50,55,48,57],
            "answer":57,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":3,
            "question":"A batsman scores 92 runs in the 15th innings and thus increases his average by 4. What is his average after the 15th innings?",
            "options":[40,32,35,36],
            "answer":36,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":4,
            "question":"The number of students in a class is 75, out of which 33 1/3 % are boys and the rest are girls. The average score in mathematics of the boys is 66 % more than that of the girls. If the average score of all the students is 66 2/3, then the average score of the girls is:",
            "options":[52,55,54,58],
            "answer":54,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":5,
            "question":"The average of 33 numbers is 74.The average of the first 17 numbers is 72.8 and that of the last 17 numbers is 77.2. If the 17th number is excluded, then what will be the average of the remaining numbers (correct to one decimal place)?",
            "options":[72.9,73.4,71.6,70.8],
            "answer":72.9,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":6,
            "question":"The average weight of a certain number of students in a group is 72 kg. If 10 students having an average weight of 78 kg leave and 4 students having an average weight of 80 kg join the group, the average weight of the students in the group decreases by 0.7 kg. The number of students initially in the group is ",
            "options":[56,46,44,54],
            "answer":46,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":7,
            "question":"The average age of 120 students in a group is 13.56 years, 35% of the number of students are girls and the rest are boys. If the ratio of the average age of boys and girls is 6:5, then what is the average age (in years) of the girls?",
            "options":[12,11.6,10,14.4],
            "answer":12,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":8,
            "question":"The average of 18 numbers is 37.5. If six numbers of average x are added to them, then the average of all the numbers increases by one. The value of x is : :",
            "options":[40,41.5,42,38.5],
            "answer":41.5,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":9,
            "question":"A party was held for 50 people on their own expenses. Out of them, 48 people paid Rs. 950 each and the other two persons paid Rs. 1200 more than the average expenses of the group. The total amount spent was :",
            "options":[75000,40000,25000,50000],
            "answer":50000,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":10,
            "question":"An art exhibition was held in the month of november. The numbers of visitors on weekdays and on weekends were 450 and 750 respectively. If the first day of the month was Monday, then what was the average number of visitors in the month ?",
            "options":[520,530,510,540],
            "answer":530,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":11,
            "question":"The owner of a bike buys petrol at the rate of Rs. 64, Rs. 80 and Rs. 320 per litre for three consecutive years. If he spends Rs. 32000 on petrol every year, then what is the average price of petrol per litre ?",
            "options":[120,84,108,96],
            "answer":96,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":12,
            "question":"A person was asked to guess his own weight. He estimated his weight to be over 70 kg but less than 80 kg. His friend estimated his weight to be more than 74 kg but less than 84 kg. His mother said that his weight is less than 78 kg. Assuming that the weights are a whole number and that the three had correctly guessed, then what is the average of the possible weights?",
            "options":[76.5,76,77,75],
            "answer":76,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":13,
            "question":"The average of a and b is 36. The average of b and c is 42. What is the difference between c and a ?",
            "options":[18,12,16,14],
            "answer":12,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":14,
            "question":"What is the average of the first 8 multiples of 6 among the natural numbers?",
            "options":[24,26,27,28],
            "answer":27,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":15,
            "question":"The average of all the prime and composite numbers upto 100 is:",
            "options":[51,50,50.5,49.5],
            "answer":50.5,
            "category":"Average"
        }
    ],
    [
        {
            "id":1,
            "question":"What is the average of the first 15 whole numbers?",
            "options":[8,7,9,10],
            "answer":7,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":2,
            "question":"Out of four numbers the average of the first three is 16 and that of the last three is 15. If the last number is 21 then the first number is:",
            "options":[28,22,21,24],
            "answer":24,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":3,
            "question":"10 years ago, the average age of a family of five members was 38 years. Now, two new members join, whose age difference is 8 years. If the present average age of the family is the same as it was 10 years ago, what is the age (in years) of the new younger member?",
            "options":[15,9,10,7],
            "answer":9,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":4,
            "question":"The average of a number and its reciprocal is 4. The average of its cube and its reciprocal is equal to:",
            "options":[256,142,288,244],
            "answer":244,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":5,
            "question":"The average of the first 1234 _______ numbers is equal to 1234.",
            "options":["odd","even","prime","natural"],
            "answer":"odd",
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":6,
            "question":"The average of the first 101 ______ numbers is equal to 102",
            "options":["natural","odd","even","perfect square"],
            "answer":"even",
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":7,
            "question":"The difference between the average of first ten prime numbers and the first ten prime numbers of two digits is:",
            "options":[14.5,16.5,12.5,13.5],
            "answer":13.5,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":8,
            "question":"The average of 1088 real numbers is zero. At most how many of them can be negative?",
            "options":[100,88,544,1087],
            "answer":1087,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":9,
            "question":"The average age of four brothers is 15 years. If their father is included, the average is increased by 5 years. The age of the father (in years) is:",
            "options":[35,40,38,36],
            "answer":40,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":10,
            "question":"In a class of 80 students, 60% participate in games and the rest do not. The average weight of the former group is 5% more than that of the latter. If the average weight of all the students is 51 1/2 kg, then what is the average weight (in kg) of the former group?",
            "options":[57.6,54.5,60,52.5],
            "answer":52.5,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":11,
            "question":"The average weight of the students in a group was 75.4 kg. Later on, four students having weights, 72.9 kg, 73.8 kg, 79.5 kg and 87.4 kg joined the group. As a result, the average weight of all the students in the group increased by 0.24 kg. What was the number of students in the group, initially?",
            "options":[46,36,50,48],
            "answer":46,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":12,
            "question":"The average of n number is 36. If each of 75% of the numbers is increased by 6 and each of the remaining numbers is decreased by 9, then the new average of the numbers is:",
            "options":[37.125,33.75,38.25,36.25],
            "answer":38.25,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":13,
            "question":"9 years ago, the average age of a family of five members was 33 yearsNow, three new members join whose ages are in ascending order with consecutive gaps of 8 years. If the present average age of the family is the same as it was 9 years ago, what is the age (in years) of the youngest new member?",
            "options":[15,17,10,9],
            "answer":10,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":14,
            "question":"The average of twelve numbers is 42. The average of the last five numbers is 40 and that of the first four numbers is 44. The 6th number is 6 less than the fifth and 5 less than the 7th number. The average of the 5th and the 7th numbers is:",
            "options":[44,44.5,43,43.5],
            "answer":44.5,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":15,
            "question":"The average weight of a certain number of students in a class is 68.5 kg. If 4 new students having weights 72.2 kg, 70.8kg, 70.3kg and 66.7 kg join the class, then the average weight of all the students increases by 300 g. The number of students in the class, initially is:",
            "options":[21,16,11,26],
            "answer":16,
            "category":"Average"
        }
    ],
    [
        {
            "id":1,
            "question":"Three numbers are such that if the average of any two of them is added to the third number, the sums obtained are 168, 174 and 180 respectively. What is the average of the original three numbers?",
            "options":[86,87,89,84],
            "answer":87,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":2,
            "question":"The total number of students in section A and B of a class is 110. The number of students in section A is 10 more than that of section B. The average score of the students in B, in a test, is 20% more than that of students in A. If the average score of all the students in the class is 72, then what is the average score of the students in A?",
            "options":[66,68,63,70],
            "answer":66,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":3,
            "question":"Four different positive numbers are written in ascending order. One-third of the average of all the four numbers is 19 less than the greatest of these numbers.If the average of the first three numbers is 12, the greatest number among the given numbers is:",
            "options":[25,22,24,21],
            "answer":24,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":4,
            "question":"The average marks of 40 students was found to be 68. If the marks of two students were incorrectly entered as 48 and 64 instead of 84 and 46 respectively, then what is the correct average?",
            "options":[68.25,68.15,68.45,68.35],
            "answer":68.45,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":5,
            "question":"In a class of 40 students, 45% are girls and the remaining are boys. If the average of the girls marks is 54 and that of the boys is 46, what is the average of the whole class?",
            "options":[49.8,49.7,49.6,49.5],
            "answer":49.6,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":6,
            "question":"The average of 27 numbers is zero. Out of them, how many may be greater than zero, at the most?",
            "options":[0,15,26,20],
            "answer":26,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":7,
            "question":"The average of the squares of numbers 1 to 5 is:",
            "options":[11,5,8,9],
            "answer":11,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":8,
            "question":"A scored 73, 76, 20 and 7 runs in four out of five innings. What should be his score in the fifth innings, if he has to make an average of 55 runs in five innings?",
            "options":[99,11,55,42],
            "answer":99,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":9,
            "question":"The average of 28 numbers is 77. The average of first 14 numbers is 74 and the average of last 15 numbers is 84. If the 14 th number is excluded, then what is the average of remaining numbers? (correct to one decimal place)",
            "options":[77,74.7,76.9,73.1],
            "answer":74.7,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":10,
            "question":"In a class of 90 students 60% are girls and remaining are boys, Average marks of boys are 63 and that of girls are 70. What are the average marks of the whole class?",
            "options":[58.9,65.3,66.7,67.2],
            "answer":67.2,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":11,
            "question":"The average of eleven numbers is 56. The average of the first three numbers is 52 and that of the next five numbers is 60. The 9th and 10th numbers are 3 and 1 more than the 11th number respectively. What is the average of 9th and 11th numbers?",
            "options":[53.5,52,52.5,54],
            "answer":53.5,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":12,
            "question":"The average of 22 numbers is 37.5. The average of the first 12 numbers is 40.6 and that of the last 12 numbers is 35.4. If 11th and 12th numbers are excluded, then what is the average of the remaining numbers?",
            "options":[36.9,37.4,36.4,37.8],
            "answer":36.9,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":13,
            "question":"The average height of some students in a group is 156 cm. If 5 students of average height 160 cm join the group, then the average height of all the students in the group increases by 0.8 cm. What is the number of students in the group?",
            "options":[20,10,25,15],
            "answer":20,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":14,
            "question":"The average of 8 consecutive even numbers written in ascending order is 17. What is the average of the last three numbers, 36 and 53?",
            "options":[32.2,29.8,31.6,31],
            "answer":31,
            "category":"Average"
        },
        {
            "id":15,
            "question":"The average score of 40 students in a class test is 45. Later on, it was found that at two places 25 was read as 35 and at one place 38 was read as 32. What is the actual average score of the class?",
            "options":[45.35,39.69,44.65,43.80],
            "answer":44.65,
            "category":"Average"
        }
    ]
]